http://susanmarielight.com

248-804-5021 Waterford, MI info@susanmarielight.com

Career Summary

Creative business development leader with over 12 years online technologies experience, including web site development, web applications and online meeting tools and 20 years experience in graphics, print and presentations. Successful, action-oriented people leader managing creative, innovative, process-driven teams supporting all groups in General Motors Corporation, including suppliers and global customers.

Experience Summary

General Motors Corporation Communications Technology Group	Operations Manager Graphics & Translations	2009-April 2009 Manage 6 person team; 10 contract workers; \$4.5M Budget
General Motors Corporation Communications Technology Group	Online Meetings Manager Online Meeting Support & Translations	2008-2009 Manage 13 person team; \$4M Budget
	Collaboration Strategy Manager Online Meeting Support gm.webex.com	2007-2008 Manage 6 person team; \$2.5M Budget
	Consultant – Web Strategist Web, Collaboration & Strategy	1999-2004 Manage 8 person team; \$1.2M Budget
General Motors Corporation GM Photographic	Web Strategy Specialist Intranet Web Sites	1998-1999 Manage 14 person team; \$400,000 Budget
	Supervisor – Web/Graphics Supervisor – Displays/Print Art Director/Designer Graphics Leader Graphics Designer	1997-1998 1994-1997 1990-1994 1988-1990 1985-1988

Education

MA Organizational Management
BA Fine Arts and Graphic Design
ITIL Certification
IT Business Certification

University of Phoenix
Eastern Michigan University
Hewlett-Packard
General Motors University

http://susanmarielight.com

248-804-5021 Waterford, MI info@susanmarielight.com

Career Objective

Secure a technology leadership position within an organization utilizing my creative and innovative leadership skills along with executing budget conscious managerial skills in support of the company's progress and success.

Experience Detail

General Motors Corporation

Renaissance Building, Detroit, MI

Operations Manager - Graphics and Translations

2009-April 2009

Global Communications

Communications Technology Group

Communications Technology Group provides technology services for GM Communications. Responsibilities include: lead three teams using one project manager, one process manager, three graphics specialists, and two supplier project managers; manage five processes; coordinate and interact with four key suppliers; conduct supplier evaluations; administer budget management for processes and teams.

- Re-established graphics team within one month and transitioned three employees to this team while continuing support for online meetings
- Manage translation services contracts worth \$3 million for North America and Southeast Europe, providing over 150 languages for press releases, brochures, websites, videos and training
- Manage on and offshore web team: team provides web changes for over 550 sites
- Manage GM's Phone Operator Service
- Utilize integration tools to establish teams, create new vision and mission along with a formal process for project and goal

Online Meetings and Translations Manager

2008-2009

Global Communications

Communications Technology Group

Communications Support Group was absorbed by GM Communications in July 2008. Transitioning employees were integrated into the GM Communications Technology Group. Responsibilities included managing the WebEx customer support team, the phone operator service process, and the web change process and team.

- Saved over \$9 million, in three years, using web change online tool developed
- Integral part of deployment initiative to change the online meeting tool to Microsoft Live Meeting from WebEx; learned and trained six people on team to be trainers
- Realized \$100,000 savings in call center costs for operator service in one year out of \$400,000 budget, also rebilling GMAC for 10% of costs after negotiating costs
- Attended Leadership Innovation seminar and integrated career templates as part of evaluation process – secured promotions for two team members

http://susanmarielight.com

248-804-5021 Waterford, MI info@susanmarielight.com

Collaboration Strategy Manager

2004 - 2008

Communications Support Group

WebEx Team, Web and Customer Support Teams

Communications Support Group provided project management, process management and customer support for meetings, events, web sites, training materials, broadcasts and videos, graphics, print and photography. Responsibilities included building, training and managing the customer team that provided support for large corporate meetings and town hall events (global), as well as deployment of WebEx online meetings.

- Managed team of six WebEx experts supporting over 150 WebEx online events in 2008 which resulted in over \$10 million in travel savings for company
- Designed and managed internal web site for WebEx (Best Practice)
- Designed, built and deployed an enrollment application, with two-step approval work flow process, to sign up new WebEx hosts
- Quarterly performance evaluations, with leader comments, focused on strengths with shared belief of open, timely communication and praise when earned

Customer Consultant – Web Strategist

1999 - 2004

Communications Support Group

Interactive Web Team

In 1999, Communications Support Group was downsized from 120 employees to 40, through use of an interviewing and testing process. Change management tools were used and the new group began to "manage the work" rather than "produce the work". Responsibilities included setting up a new structure and process from "producing" to "managing" projects, through supplier resources. Three teams were created for web collaboration and strategy to support over 140 internal requests for new web sites.

- Trained and managed team of four employees and four contract employees and bid projects to five suppliers
- Worked with WebEx to learn tool and train new team
- Worked with purchasing to finalize purchase order for WebEx to be used globally

General Motors Corporation

Argonaut Building, Detroit, MI

Team Leader 1998 – 1999

Communications Support Group

Web Strategy Specialist

As a web strategy specialist, consultation with customers required support for both static web interfaces and web application development. Responsibilities included strategic direction and day-to-day management of web project managers, hiring of contract web programmers, and development and management of project budgets for customers from every business unit in GM.

- Created "Project Site" to acquire bids, track projects, document changes, and collaborate electronically between suppliers, customers and project managers
- Built team with six employees and eight contract employees

http://susanmarielight.com

248-804-5021 Waterford, MI info@susanmarielight.com

Team Leader 1997 – 1998

Communications Support Group

Web Creative Development Team

Often called the "Wild, Wild, West" time of the internet, this period was active with new initiatives, changing from print to web, creating new online interfaces for information. Building a team from scratch of project managers and programmers with new technology was exciting and rewarding. Responsibilities included management and professional development of coordinators, web authors, developers, graphic designers and technical partners as well as, setting standards, writing proposals, benchmarking suppliers, training and learning. Contract employees were hired to fill positions throughout GM, for web work, with management from a central team. The team of eight designed and built many of the first web sites that started the General Motors intranet, called Socrates.

- Developed business plan, using web site for presentation, gaining approval for first web team in GM worked with team over weekend to create site
- Gathered requirements, wrote proposals and estimated over 70 web projects
- Supervised people using learning organization methodology, trial and error and lesson sharing through team meetings and daily interaction about new techniques

Supervisor 1994 – 1996

General Motors Photographic

Presentation/Display/Print

General Motors Photographic was an internal group that provided communication support for internal customers for broadcasts and video, displays, presentations, graphics, print, and photography, servicing all groups in General Motors. Responsibilities included supervising a team of creative designers, illustrators and project coordinators, estimate projects, write proposals, manage suppliers, and hire required supplier resources for on-site support, training, development and evaluation of employees.

- Created 50th anniversary of World War II display in General Motors Building, using a great team of creative, resourceful, and knowledgeable resources. Rave reviews from the press in the downtown area.
- Managed two shifts of 17 people, as requests for presentations and print materials grew due to beginning of computer use for art work.

Art Director/Designer

1990 - 1994

General Motors Photographic

Marketing Services Group

While with General Motors Photographic, the Marketing Services Group created and produced direct mail marketing materials for dealerships. Responsibilities included developing and designing marketing proposals and direct mail materials, provide desktop publishing, disk preparation and pre-press to print follow-up.

- Lead designer for Chevrolet Direct Mail Program and the GM Protection Plan Direct Mail Program
- Key player winning bid against eleven competitors for large Service Direct Mail account. Created 70 super comps in two weeks, working with internal production team of three

http://susanmarielight.com

248-804-5021 Waterford, MI info@susanmarielight.com

Graphics Leader 1988 – 1990

General Motors Photographic – Graphic Line

Warren, MI

General Motors Photographic Graphic Line was a small group that provided graphic art and presentation materials for events, meetings and displays for management and executives in all groups in General Motors.

• Responsibilities included leading a group of 15 employees, meeting with clients to receive job, estimate jobs, delegate work, and follow-up of each job to completion.

Graphics Designer

1985 - 1988

General Motors Photographic – Graphic Line

Warren, MI

Responsibilities included layout, design, keylines, type specification, slide art production and coordination, poster displays, client contact and project estimation.

 Provided multi-media presentations for the General Motors Board of Directors that required nine slide projectors. Three overlapping slides created a panorama view and movement onscreen, which was new technology for the time.

Additional Knowledge

Leadership and Supervision Fundamentals

1997

General Motors University

Technology Seminars

1997-1999

Siggraph, Adobe, AdTech, Middleware, Internet World

Microsoft; Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project, Net Meeting, Live Meeting

Adobe; Photoshop, Acrobat, InDesign, Flash, Adobe Connect IBM/HP/Cisco; Lotus Notes, ChannelNet Sitebuilder, WebEx